<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: learning | NoisyCode]]></title>
  <link href="http://noisycode.com/blog/categories/learning/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://noisycode.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-14T20:29:56-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://noisycode.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jeremy Pierre]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[IX and the throughput/latency tradeoff]]></title>
    <link href="http://noisycode.com/blog/2015/01/14/ix-and-the-throughput-slash-latency-tradeoff/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-14T19:22:22-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://noisycode.com/blog/2015/01/14/ix-and-the-throughput-slash-latency-tradeoff</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since <a href="https://twitter.com/saemg">Saem</a> put me onto the Coursera <a href="https://class.coursera.org/learning-003">&ldquo;Learning How To Learn&rdquo;</a> course and <a href="https://twitter.com/tavisrudd">Tavis</a> (as well as <a href="https://twitter.com/tylerweir">Tyler</a> iirc) pointed me at <a href="http://www.scotthyoung.com/blog/">Scott Young</a>, I&rsquo;ve been trying to figure out how to better approach learning all of the material I try to throw at myself.</p>

<p>This coming Monday for the <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/0/communities/110886264051164890990">Polyglot reading group</a> we&rsquo;re covering the <a href="https://www.usenix.org/conference/osdi14/technical-sessions/presentation/belay">IX protected dataplane OS</a> <a href="https://www.usenix.org/system/files/conference/osdi14/osdi14-paper-belay.pdf">paper</a> which describes a set of tradeoffs that operating systems must make when deciding how to handle IO (network in this case).</p>

<p>While initially skimming the paper to try to figure out how I might chunk it to build a more cohesive understanding, I realized that I had an intuitive grip on the tradeoff between throughput and latency but I&rsquo;d never tried to properly define it for myself.  Being able to clearly define something I think is a mark of actual understanding and builds the ability to leverage it.  I figured this would be a good exercise in that spirit and both Dr Oakley and Scott Young seem to agree from what I&rsquo;ve seen so far.</p>

<h1>My Attempt</h1>

<p>Describe throughput, latency, and the tradeoff between them as generally as possible but with a view to how they pertain to the IX paper.</p>

<h2>Throughput</h2>

<p>Is a measure of how much <em>uninterrupted</em> work can be done.</p>

<h2>Latency</h2>

<p>Is a measure of how long it takes from submission of some work until its completion.</p>

<p>I think &ldquo;submission&rdquo; is likely interchangeable with any of the following if you prefer:</p>

<ul>
<li>definition</li>
<li>creation</li>
<li>identification</li>
</ul>


<h2>The Tradeoff</h2>

<p>In a system with limited capacity to do work, latency is proportional to the ability to interrupt existing work.  If interruption of current work is <em>not</em> permitted, meaning existing work proceeds with <em>no breaks</em>, the latency is equivalent to the time it takes to complete the pre-existing work because the system cannot do the new work until it finishes the <em>existing</em> work.  If interruptions <em>are</em> permitted without restriction, throughput is entirely bound by the frequency of interruptions.</p>

<p>In a system that preempts work, the balance is struck by limiting the frequency of interruptions.</p>

<p>In a cooperative system, the balance is struck by yielding control after an alotted amount of work is done (note that this depends on altruistic workers).</p>

<h1>Next</h1>

<p>I&rsquo;m going to try to apply this same sort of approach for simpler base concepts.  I think it&rsquo;s roughly in line with the <a href="http://www.scotthyoung.com/learnonsteroids/grab/TranscriptFeynman.pdf">Feynman technique</a> albeit simplified for the moment perhaps.</p>

<p>If you disagree with my definition with respect to the IX paper, I&rsquo;d love to hear about it.  As mentioned I&rsquo;ve only skimmed the paper so far and so it&rsquo;s entirely likely my definition and/or understanding will change a bit as I dig in deeper.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
